Tom Hiatt

Tashkent Region, Uzbekistan



tomhiatt@gmail.com



linkedin.com/in/tom-hiatt-8180b037

Summary

Digital Health Expert providing applied solutions in eHealth, mHealth, infectious diseases, health emergencies, data visualization, country development, effective social interventions, and social business/enterprise in various countries (Philippines, Papua New Guinea, Mongolia, Zimbabwe, Switzerland, Viet Nam).

Portfolio: http://bit.ly/tomhiatt

Experience



Public Health Specialist

World Health Organization

Jun 2022 - Present (11 months)

Advising the National TB Programmes of 5 Central Asia countries - Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan, Tajikistan, Turkmenistan, Uzbekistan.

🚇 Public Health Specialist, Tuberculosis & Rabies

World Health Organization

May 2019 - Jun 2022 (3 years 2 months)

Supported massive scale-up of tuberculosis (TB) screening, testing, treatment and prevention under the Race to End TB campaign resulting in a 15% year-on-year increase in cases found.

Developed and designed four mobile apps for the End TB App Suite (http://ntp.doh.gov.ph/apps) - CARE TB for supporting patient care; RACE TB for surveillance and monitoring; LEAD TB for programmatic management; and GUIDE TB for eLearning and eReference. Also developed the COVID-19 surveillance system, COVIDKAYA.

Supported the National Rabies Prevention and Control Program with joint annual reports from the human and animal sectors, improved data flows, technical advisories, national vaccination campaigns, a rapid response toolkit, and health promotion.

Created the contact tracing handbook to support the national COVID-19 response.



Monitoring And Evaluation Specialist, Health Emergencies

World Health Organization

Jan 2017 - Jun 2019 (2 years 6 months)

Created an internal implementation monitoring systems to ensure effective results-based activities were conducted according to the WHO Planning, Budgeting and Monitoring Framework.

Planned and conducted a training workshop on After Action Reviews and

Simulation Exercises.

Created an M&E database to collect and store all M&E activities under the IHR Monitoring and Evaluation Framework as well as National Action Plans and Pandemic Preparedness Plans.



Epidemiologist, Tuberculosis and Leprosy

World Health Organization

Jan 2012 - Dec 2016 (5 years)

Led the analysis and data visualization development for eight annual global TB control reports (2007 to 2014 datasets).

Conducted in-depth TB programme reviews in Viet Nam, Mongolia, Papua New Guinea and the Philippines to assess progress and recommend improvements for Ministries of Health.

Developed mobile apps for TB and leprosy including programme directory and leprosy disability assessment tool with high user acceptance.



🔔 Health Data Analyst, Tuberculosis

World Health Organization

Jan 2007 - Jan 2012 (5 years 1 month)

Created four Global TB control reports as part of core writing team (www.who.int/tb/publications/ global_report). Led data management and analysis for "Improving TB estimates" workshops in all 6 WHO regions.

Taught 10 plus trainings for the WHO Health Data Forum for over 100 global health professionals on data analysis and visualization. Conceptualized re-design of order management system for Global Drug Facility. Designed TB technical assistance coordination web tool.

Education

London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, U. of London

MSc, Epidemiology 2010 - 2013

BYU Brigham Young University

BA, Visual art, Media art

2001 - 2005

Though unusual, this degree actually prepared me immensely for a career in public health. My art skills brought me overseas and opened my mind to the global community and diversity of opinions, norms and values. It also taught me to think through challenges from new perspectives. Producing films and television programmes brought about the skills required to lead a team and persuade others with soft influence. Having a strong sense for aesthetics and working with others has repeatedly proven beneficial in the most diverse of circumstances.

Skills

R • Stata • Data Collection • Reports • Data Processing • Data Visualization • Epidemiology • Analysis • Global Health • Data Management